# MILAN WIEDEMANN

Wolfson College, Linton Road, OX2 6UD Oxford milan.wiedemann@gmail.com  $\diamond$  www.milanwiedemann.com

#### PERSONAL SUMMARY

I am a PhD candidate at the University of Oxford investigating processes of change in cognitive therapy for Posttraumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD). Testing the theoretical models underpinning cognitive therapy for PTSD has strengthened my understanding of the importance that clinical interventions are rooted in empirical science and continually evaluated and refined through research. I appreciate the importance of innovative research projects testing and evaluating technological advances in clinical psychology. I value, advocate, and implement open science practices in my work.

## **EDUCATION AND QUALIFICATIONS**

## University of Oxford

October 2016 - Present

DPhil in Experimental Psychology at the Oxford Centre for Anxiety Disorders and Trauma

Thesis: Processes of Change in Cognitive Therapy for Posttraumatic Stress Disorder Supervised by Prof. Anke Ehlers and Prof. David M. Clark

#### Technische Universität Braunschweig

August 2013 - September 2015

MSc in Psychology

Study focus: Clinical Psychology

## Technische Universität Braunschweig

August 2011 - September 2013

BSc in Psychology

# University of Groningen

September 2010 - August 2011

BSc in Psychology

#### DRK-Rettungsschule Goslar

January 2011- February 2011

Rettungssanitäter (in English 'Paramedic')

#### CLINICAL & RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

#### University of Oxford

October 2016 - Present

Part-time Research Assistant, Oxford Centre for Anxiety Disorders and Trauma

Oxford, UK

- · Creating videos for training clinical psychologists in specialised cognitive behavioural treatments.
- · Teaching and supervising Research Assistants in filming and editing techniques.

# University of Oxford

April 2015 - August 2016

Research Assistant, Oxford Centre for Anxiety Disorders and Trauma

Oxford, UK

- · Production of patient testimonials and educational videos together with clinical psychologists.
- · Animation of psycho-educational illustrations.
- · Administration of text, video and audio content for online therapy programmes.

## Technische Universität Braunschweig

September 2012 - March 2015

Part-time Research Assistant, Institute of Clinical Psychology

Braunschweig, GER

- · Conducting clinical interviews with adolescents for a longitudinal study.
- · Setting up and managing large databases for national and international research teams.

#### Local Health Authority Berlin Pankow

Intern, Social Psychiatric Department

February 2012 - March 2012 Berlin, GER

- · Conducting initial clinical interviews as well as follow-up interviews under supervision.
- · Making house calls as part of a multidisciplinary team in emergency situations.

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

## University of Oxford

January 2018 - February 2018

Demonstrator, Department of Experimental Psychology

Oxford, UK

· Module: Psychological Disorders and Individual Differences.

#### Technische Universität Braunschweig

April 2014 - March 2015

Teaching Assistant, Institute of Clinical Psychology

Braunschweig, GER

 $\cdot$  Module: Practical Course of Psychological Diagnostics.

· Module: Fundamentals of Psychological Diagnostics.

## Technische Universität Braunschweig

September 2012 - January 2014

Teaching Assistant, Institute of Methodology and Biopsychology

Braunschweig, GER

· Module: Laboratory Experience and Analysis with Statistical Software.

#### ADDITIONAL EXPERIENCE

## University of Oxford

July 2017 - September 2017

Part-time Research Assistant, Faculty of History

Oxford, UK

· Production of promotional video for the workshop: Changing lives: Understanding what enables children growing up in adversity to thrive in modern Britain.

#### Arbeiter-Samariter-Bund Braunschweig

May 2010 - March 2015

Part-time Paramedic

Braunschweig, GER

- $\cdot$  Medical care during the qualified transport of patients.
- · First aid and emergency treatment of patients.
- · Independent ambulance coach driver in the in-house emergency centre.

#### Arbeiter-Samariter-Bund Braunschweig

July 2008 - March 2009

Civilian Service

Braunschweig, GER

- · Getting trained as a 'Paramedic' (in German: Rettungssanitäter).
- · Medical care during the qualified transport of patients.
- · Independent ambulance coach driver in the in-house emergency centre.

#### **SCHOLARSHIPS**

## Mental Health Research UK

May 2018

Travel Grant

## University of Oxford, Wolfson College

June 2017

Travel Grant

# Mental Health Research UK

October 2016

PhD Scholarship

## Erasmus plus

February 2015

Graduate Student Scholarship

#### SELECTED PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

<b>DeGPT Autumn School</b> Deutschsprachige Gesellschaft für Psychotraumatologie, 4 days	October 2018
Psychological Networks Summer School University of Amsterdam, 5 days	August 2018
Summer School of Advanced Quantitative Methods University of Oxford, Department of Education, 5 days	May 2018
Testing for Mediation and Moderation Using Mplus Figure It Out - Statistical Consultancy and Training, 1 day	June 2017
Multilevel Analysis for Longitudinal Data Universität Landau, Methodenzentrum, 3 days	February 2016
Structural Equation Models for Longitudinal Data Universität Landau, Methodenzentrum, 2 days	February 2016

#### TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Statistics & Data science	R, GitHub, Mplus, JASP, jamovi, Praat, SPSS
Scientific writing	R Markdown, Zotero, LaTeX, BibTeX, Microsoft Office
Video & Audio editing	Final Cut X, Audacity, iZotope RX

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

## Peer-reviewed

Wild, J., Warnock-Parkes, E., Grey, N., Stott, R., **Wiedemann, M**, Canvin, L., ... Ehlers, A. (2016). Internet-delivered cognitive therapy for PTSD: A development pilot series. *European Journal of Psychotraumatology*, 7(1). doi:10.3402/ejpt.v7.31019

# Software

Wiedemann, M. (2018). lcsm: An R package for specifying and analysing latent change score models using lavaan. Retrieved from https://github.com/milanwiedemann/lcsm

Wiedemann, M, Thew, G. R., Stott, R., & Ehlers, A. (2019). Suddengains: An r package to identify sudden gains in longitudinal data. *PsyArXiv Preprints*. doi:10.31234/osf.io/2wa84

# **PRESENTATIONS**

# Conference presentations

Wiedemann, M., Clark, D. M., & Ehlers, A. (2017). Predictors and processes of sudden gains in cognitive therapy for PTSD. European Association for Behavioural and Cognitive Therapies, Ljubljana, Slovenia.

# Invited talks

- Wiedemann, M. (2015). Mental health care in England overview of the improving access to psychological therapies (IAPT) programme. Local Health Authority Berlin Pankow.
- Wiedemann, M. (2016). Digital methods in internet-delivered cognitive therapy for PTSD: Results from a pilot study. *Local Health Authority Berlin Pankow*.
- Wiedemann, M., Clark, D. M., & Ehlers, A. (2018a). Processes of change in cognitive therapy for PTSD. *University of Groningen*, WEIRD Seminar Series.
- Wiedemann, M., Clark, D. M., & Ehlers, A. (2018b). Sudden gains in cognitive therapy for PTSD Can large and stable improvements between sessions help us understand how therapy works? University of Exeter, Mood Disorder Centre, The Think-Tank Seminar.